Finding Aid for School of Nursing Alumni Association (University of Michigan) records, 1909-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Nursing Alumni Association (University of Michigan) records
1909-1998
University of Michigan. School of Nursing. Alumni Association.
87297 Bimu C276 2
Organizational records, correspondence, topical files, printed material, collected material regarding the careers of individual alumni of the University of Michigan School of Nursing; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
4 linear feet
2 oversize folders
The first accession was donated by the School of Nursing Alumni Association (Donor No. 7032 ) in 1984. Periodic additions have been received.
The collection is open to research.
The School of Nursing Alumnae Association was formed in 1900 and changed its name to the Nurses Alumni Association in 1969. The name was changed again in 1993, to the Nursing Alumni Society, and administrative control was placed within the School of Nursing. Still an active organization, its purpose is to advance the interests of the University of Michigan School of Nursing and to promote good fellowship among graduates.
Planning reunions is only one activity of the Association. Its members also offer the Shirley C. Titus Scholarship to a nursing student each year. The Scholarship was started by the graduating class of 1930 with $250. By 1980, the endowment had grown to over $30,000. The Association has also been an active part of the University of Michigan Alumni Association and several members have served on the Class Officers Council. The Association also publishes a newsletter several times a year which informs members of the activities of other alumni.
The records of the School of Nursing Alumni Association of the University of Michigan date from 1907 to 1993, and measure four linear feet. In addition to documenting the growth of the organization and the interests and activities of the alumni, the collection also includes information about the development of nursing as a profession. The records include organizational records, correspondence, topical files, printed material, collected material regarding the careers of individual alumni of the University of Michigan School of Nursing, and photographs.
Subjects:
Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Photographs.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Classes.Classes.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Organizational Records
  Organizational Records, 1909-1998, contain the constitution, by-laws and minutes of the Association. Also included are financial records dating from 1924 to 1998.
  - Constitution, Bylaws and Policies, 1909-1978 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Meetings
    - June 1910-May 1911 (Box 1)
    - May 1911-October 1925 (Box 1)
    - January 1926-October 1940 (Box 1)
    - November 1940-June 1947 (Box 1)
    - January 1948-June 1954 (Box 1)
    - June 1954-September 1958 (Box 1)
    - January 1959-November 1963 (Box 1)
  - Officer's Duties, circa 1977 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Reports
    - 1932-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1998 (Box 1)
  - Financial Ledgers
    - 1924-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1933 (Box 1)
    - 1934-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1942-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1962 (Box 2)
  - Statement of Account, 1954-1972 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence, 1907-1980, is arranged chronologically and includes official correspondence of the Association and letters from members. Included in the early correspondence are letters from alumnae who worked abroad and wrote about their experiences.
  - 1907-1930 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - 1931-1940 (Box 2)
  - 1943-1956 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - 1960-1984 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files are arranged alphabetically and document the activities of the Association. Of interest are two surveys done in the 1920s by Shirley Titus who was Director of Nursing Service and the School of Nursing for six years.
  - Alumnae Loan Fund, 1917-1949 (Box 2)
    (scattered dates)
  - Alumnae Room Committee, 1964-1978 (Box 2)
  - American Red Cross Association, 1917-1918 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1970-1978 (Box 2)
  - Dean Search and Study Committee, 1969-1971; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Distinguished Alumni Lecture
    - 1969-1979 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - 1970-1974, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Educational Concerns, Committee on, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Honorary Members, 1931; 1954; undated (Box 2)
  - Membership Lists, [1893-1939], 1931-1952 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Nurses Association, 1919-1941 (Box 2)
  - Nursing Pins, 1957-1983 (Box 2)
  - President's Files
    - Dorothy Bissell, 1953-1956 (Box 2)
    - Esther Warzynski, 1956-1959 (Box 2)
  - Reunions
    - Programs, 1907-1962 (Box 2)
    - 1941 (Box 2)
    - 1950 (Box 2)
    - (class of 1941), 1981 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - School of Nursing Historical Material, [1886-1939] (Box 3)
  - Shirley Titus Scholarship Fund, 1932-1963; 1978 (Box 3)
  - Sick Nurses Relief Fund, 1931-1948 (Box 3)
  - Surveys
    - Organization of Nursing Schools, 1925-1926 (Box 3)
    - Psychological Tests, 1926-1927 (Box 3)
  - Uniforms, 1927-1960 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1909-1954 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1914-1965 (Box 3)
- Alumni Personal Papers
  Alumni Personal Papers includes the papers of three graduates. Minnie Holzhauser worked as a nurse in Bursah, India in the early 1900s and Olive McDonald was a nurse during World War II with the University of Michigan affiliated 298th General Hospital. Thelma Stegeman's manuscript, Sunshine and Shadow, is a fictional account of her experiences in the School of Nursing. Stegeman, who graduated in 1924, was head nurse at the University of Michigan Health Service Clinic for more than 30 years.
  - McDonald, Olive H., 1942-1947
    - Florence Nightingale Certificate, 1856 (Box 3)
  - Stegeman, Thelma I., 1971 (Box 3)
  - Ziegler, Minnie Holzhauser, 1913-1922 (Box 3)
- Printed Material
  Printed Material includes five journals published by the Alumni Association between 1907 and 1914, directories of members and the News Bulletin. The Bulletin is mailed to members of the Association and contains notices of reunions and, principally, news of alumni by class.
  - Directories, 1950; 1960 (Box 3)
  - Annual Dinner and Meeting Programs, 1985-1991 (Box 3)
  - Journal of the Alumnae Association, 1907-1914 (Box 3)
  - News Bulletin
    - 1937-1951 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
    - 1953-1958 (Box 3)
    - 1959-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1966-1992 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  Photographs include class pictures, photos of reunions, nursing members, and nursing-related university buildings.
  - Album (snapshots of students, campus, hospitals, staff, 1959 reunions), 1910-1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Class of (loose photographs from album), 1913 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Class Photographs, 1890-1910 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Class Photographs, 1911-1920 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Class Photographs, 1921-1930 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Class Photographs, 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Class Photographs, 1942-1944; 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Student Groups and Clubs, 1929-1934 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Individuals, A-J
    - Adams, Dr. Theodore, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Birk, Miss, 1920s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Brown, Grace, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Cartwill, Miss, 1920s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Culp, David, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Easton, Charlotte D., 1903 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Emerson, Elsie, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Giles, Mary, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Henderson, Frances, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Henderson, P.M., undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Ide, Dr., 1926 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Individuals, K-O
    - Koch, Blossom, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Leary, Ann, 1911-1912 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Lisle, Dorothy (with children), 1925 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Love, Agnes, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Maxwell, Ina, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Menhennet, Ella, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Meyers, Jessie, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Neelands, Ethel, 1911; 1913 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Niensma, Frederica, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Osterbloom, Margaret, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Individuals, P-Z
    - Pemberton, Miss, circa 1910 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Richards, Linda, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Robb, Isabel Hampton, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Sanquist, L.K., 1946 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Schell, V., 1938 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Scully, Patrick Henry, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Spier, Elsa, circa 1915 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Svoboda, Elsie, 1926 (Box 4)
    - Tasker, Children of Dorothy Stannard ('22) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Wines-Murphy, Anna ('34), with children (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Wubbena, Talka, 1914; 1931 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Head Nurses, 1927-1937 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Nursing Administrators: Portraits
    - Darling, Cyrennus (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Nancrede, Charles Beylard Guerard de (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Peterson, Reuben (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Read, Genevieve (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Staff [14], 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Nursing Superintendents and Directors: Portraits
    - Haarter, Mary, 1906-1909 (Folder UBImum/C276)
    - Holt, Elizabeth (Folder UBImum/C276)
    - Pindell, Jane, 1913-1915 (Folder UBImum/C276)
    - Pemberton, Fantine, 1915-1918 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Welsh, Mary, 1918-1922 (Folder UBImum/C276)
    - Lake, Alice, 1923-1925 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Titus, Shirley, 1925-1930 (Folder UBImum/C276)
    - Durell, Marian, 1930-1940 (Folder UBImum/C276)
    - Reddig, Rhoda, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Nursing Groups: Instructors, Students, Homeopathic Hospital, Meeting of Detroit Club, State League of Nursing, Misc. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Reunions, Class of, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Reunions, Classes of, 1905-1929 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Reunions, Classes of, 1930s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Reunions, Classes of, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Reunions, Classes of, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Alumnae, Mixed Classes (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Hospitals, University of Michigan (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous [24] (Box 4, Folder 24)